<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog</id>
    <title>Hari's world Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Hari's world Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summary of ADHD podcast by Andrew Huberman]]></title>
        <id>https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary</id>
        <link href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary"/>
        <updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have read a lot about my condition and this is a valuable resource regarding the inner working of a ADHD brain. Thanks to Andrew Huberman for the wonderful studies he have done in the concepts of ADHD. Truly admiring his great works.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have read a lot about my condition and this is a valuable resource regarding the inner working of a ADHD brain. Thanks to <a href="https://www.hubermanlab.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Andrew Huberman</a> for the wonderful studies he have done in the concepts of ADHD. Truly admiring his great works.</p>
<p>Title: <strong>ADHD and How any can improve their focus</strong> <br>
Video: <a href="https://youtu.be/hFL6qRIJZ_Y" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>ADHD &amp; How Anyone Can Improve Their Focus| Youtube</strong></a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-is-adhd-">How is ADHD ?<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How is ADHD ?" title="Direct link to How is ADHD ?" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#how-is-adhd-">​</a></h2>
<p>People with ADHD have poor attention &amp; high impulsivity.
People with ADHD can have hyperfocus in things they really enjoy or intriged by but they cannot simple focus on things that don't want to do. In real life most of the things we do for living are not things we are interested to.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="time-perception">Time perception<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Time perception" title="Direct link to Time perception" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#time-perception">​</a></h2>
<p>One of the major challenge ADHD people face is the time perception. This is the reason why they procrastinate. But the interesting thing is that if they are given a deadline they can somehow perceive time very well.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="piling-system">Piling system<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Piling system" title="Direct link to Piling system" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#piling-system">​</a></h2>
<p>ADHD people use a piling system for organising and most of the time it may not work for them.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="working-memory">Working memory<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Working memory" title="Direct link to Working memory" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#working-memory">​</a></h2>
<p>People with ADHD can have teriffic memory of the past events, upcoming events however one vital memory called working memory is not proper for them.</p>
<p>Working memory is the ability to keep specific information online, to recycle it in your brain so that you can use it in immediate or short term. Example if someone verbally given their phone number and when you tries to type on your phone/ book you forget it immediately.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="dopamine">Dopamine<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Dopamine" title="Direct link to Dopamine" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#dopamine">​</a></h2>
<p>It is a neuro-modulator and creates hightened state of focus. It tends to shrink our visual world and it makes us pay attention to the things outside and beyond the confines of our skin/ physical work. Dopamine is a drive to do something in the physical world.</p>
<p>It also has role in changing the way we perceive the world.</p>
<p>Proper production of dopamine will narrow our visual and auditory world.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="neural-circuits">Neural circuits<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Neural circuits" title="Direct link to Neural circuits" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#neural-circuits">​</a></h2>
<p>There are 2 main cirucuits w.r.t attention and dopammine in ADHD.</p>
<ol>
<li>Default mode network</li>
<li>Task Mode Network</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="1-default-mode-network">1. Default Mode Network<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 1. Default Mode Network" title="Direct link to 1. Default Mode Network" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#1-default-mode-network">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Network which are active when we are not doing anything.</li>
<li>Default mode network include the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (front-top-side part of the brain ).</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="2-task-mode-network">2. Task mode Network<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2. Task mode Network" title="Direct link to 2. Task mode Network" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#2-task-mode-network">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Network which is goal oriented. It is a different set of brain area from default mode Network.</li>
<li>It is also in prefrontal cortex but in diffent part to default mode network. It is at Medial Prefrontal Cortex (MPC in short, Front Centre part of the brain ).</li>
<li>MPC communicates with other parts of the brain mainly to suppress the impulses. It is shutting down your desire to stand up or scratch the side of the cheek.</li>
</ul>
<p>But there is communication btw task mode and default mode networks.</p>
<p>The two networks have a lot of communication in a neuro-typical person. But in a person with ADHD or a person with low sleep the 2 networks are not synchronized.</p>
<p>In a neuro-typical person the default mode and task mode networks are anti-correlated. That is they are opposing to each other to balance one another. But in a person with ADHD these 2 networks are co-related and they cannot control or balance each other.</p>
<p>What #dopamine is doing in this context is that it is acting as a conductor in a musical concert which make sure which mode should be active at a particular time. That is dopamine make them anti-corelated and helps balance each other.</p>
<p>This raises 2 questions in ADHD, whether #dopamine is not sufficiantly high enough levels or #dopamine conducting everything wrong.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="low-dopamine-in-adhd-stimulant-use-and-abuse">Low dopamine in ADHD, Stimulant use and Abuse.<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Low dopamine in ADHD, Stimulant use and Abuse." title="Direct link to Low dopamine in ADHD, Stimulant use and Abuse." href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#low-dopamine-in-adhd-stimulant-use-and-abuse">​</a></h2>
<p>In year 2015m a research paper came but in an excellent journal in Biological Psychiatry (Author name: Spencer). This paper normalizes the fact of low dopamine hypothesis in ADHD.</p>
<p>It explains when dopamine levels are too low in particular areas of the brain, it leads to unnecessary firing of the neurons in the brain which is unrelated to the task we are trying to do. It can be like an instrumental concert without a conductor.</p>
<p>Even before such dopamine deficient hypothesis, in 1940s and 1960s we can see such people with ADHD tend to use recreational drugs or they tend to indulge in non-drug stimulants such as coffee, espresso or smoking half pack of cigarettes. Some others with access to street drugs they used cocaine, amphetamine etc.</p>
<p>All these drugs will increase the levels of dopamine in the brain especially in the regions which regulate attention and task related and default mode networks.</p>
<p>Some children who do not have access to any of these drugs can be seen easting too much sugary food, coke which creates a sudden rush in dopamine.This makes them able to calm themselves. But when children who do not have ADHD consumes this they will become hyperactive due to enormously high production of dopamine.</p>
<p><strong>"LOW LEVELS OF DOPAMINE IS THE MAIN ISSUE WITH PEOPLE WITH ADHD."</strong></p>
<p>Thus giving dopamine energic compounds to people with ADHD will somehow increase the ability to focus.</p>
<p>So major drugs developed and marketed by pharmaceutical companies are</p>
<ol>
<li>Ritalin</li>
<li>Adderral</li>
<li>Modafinil</li>
</ol>
<p>These all drugs will increase the levels of dopamine in the regions of brains that manages the 2 modes.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="ritalin">Ritalin<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Ritalin" title="Direct link to Ritalin" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#ritalin">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Ritalin is a stimulus prescribed for ADHD and narcolepsy (Condition in which people tend to fall asleep during the day time quite a lot, excessive day time sleepiness and also may sleep when they get excited).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ritalin is the oldest drug in use.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Ritalin also called as <strong>methylphenidate</strong> [ METH-il-FEN-i-date ]</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="addrell">Addrell<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Addrell" title="Direct link to Addrell" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#addrell">​</a></h3>
<p>Addrell is now the most prescribed drug for treating ADHD.</p>
<p>Both Addrell and Modafinil helps to treat narcolepsy as well.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="pharmaco-kinetics-kinetics-means-movement">Pharmaco-kinetics (Kinetics means movement)<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Pharmaco-kinetics (Kinetics means movement)" title="Direct link to Pharmaco-kinetics (Kinetics means movement)" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#pharmaco-kinetics-kinetics-means-movement">​</a></h2>
<p>(This term means how the drug works.)</p>
<p>All these drugs are share the almost same compounds as cocaine and meth which are greatly habit forming and abusive.
They are not exactly the same as meth or cocaine but similar. Their net effect in the brain and body is the same which is to increase the dopamine but also the levels of neuro-modulators called epinephrine or neurotransmitter, also called as noradrenaline amd to some extend increase the levels of serotonin in the brain and blood.</p>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>info</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p><strong>Serotine</strong> is more about feeling calm and relaxed.</p></div></div>
<p>It is good to prescribe stimulants early i life and it will be effective as neuroplasticity of brain decreases as we age.</p>
<p>We should discourage the use of street drugs of any kind as there is nobody to regulate the dosage and also quality is not assured. Also we do not need such heavy dosage for an ADHD person.</p>
<p>25-35% of college students and working professionals in US (in age between 17 t 35) use black market Addrell to function properly and focus on their daily life even though they are not diagnosed by ADHD. Now consumption of Addrelll without prescription is higher than the consumption of cannabis at age group of 17-30.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="nicotin-and-caffine">Nicotin and Caffine<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nicotin and Caffine" title="Direct link to Nicotin and Caffine" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#nicotin-and-caffine">​</a></h3>
<p>Nicotine and Caffeine are also used in high amount for energy of focus, Nicotine should not be used due to high risk of cancer.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="case-study-on-children">Case study on children<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Case study on children" title="Direct link to Case study on children" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#case-study-on-children">​</a></h2>
<p>In this research Andrew Huberman came across a couple who are in close relationship with him. A child of them have ADHD and the parents have deep knowledge in ADHD. So Huberman asked some questions to them:</p>
<ol>
<li>Will you give Amphetamine to their kid ?
Answer from the couple was that they will use the lowest dosage required and moderate as they grow up which will help them learn attention. This will benefit the kid in a larger way.</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="food-control">Food control<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Food control" title="Direct link to Food control" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#food-control">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Controlling allergic food like gluten, milk, sugar helps to control the hyper activity.</li>
<li>Elimination of simple sugars and high sugar are highly appreciated.</li>
<li>Avoiding all the food allergic is not ideal as it can cause severe auto-immune issues when consumed accidentally.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="omega-3-fatty-acids">Omega 3 fatty acids<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Omega 3 fatty acids" title="Direct link to Omega 3 fatty acids" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#omega-3-fatty-acids">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Getting <strong>1000 mg</strong> or more of Omega 3 fatty acids (fish oil), which known to have anti-depressant effects works better for people with ADHD as well.</li>
<li>It also benefits the immune system, cardio vascular system.</li>
</ul>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-info admonition_xJq3 alert alert--info"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M7 2.3c3.14 0 5.7 2.56 5.7 5.7s-2.56 5.7-5.7 5.7A5.71 5.71 0 0 1 1.3 8c0-3.14 2.56-5.7 5.7-5.7zM7 1C3.14 1 0 4.14 0 8s3.14 7 7 7 7-3.14 7-7-3.14-7-7-7zm1 3H6v5h2V4zm0 6H6v2h2v-2z"></path></svg></span>info</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>All these regarding food control are good but their effect on focus and attention is only modest, THey have only modulatory role like sleep in ADHD.</p></div></div>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="behavioural-changes-to-adapt">Behavioural changes to adapt<a class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Behavioural changes to adapt" title="Direct link to Behavioural changes to adapt" href="https://my-blog-pu0.pages.dev/blog/adhd-andrew-huberman-podcast-summary#behavioural-changes-to-adapt">​</a></h2>
<p>Huberman suggest a book called <strong>"Altered traits"</strong>.</p>
<p>People with ADHD will have attentional blink which is a condition when you are in a race for finding multiple things, you may involved in finding one of them but misses the second one. For e.e. reading a documentation and finding a single thing but misses others, this is because ADHD people are over focused in finding a particular piece of information. This is called as <strong>attentional blinks</strong> and it is more in ADHD people than in normal people.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Over focusing on something and not able to realize other things.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-danger admonition_xJq3 alert alert--danger"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 12 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M5.05.31c.81 2.17.41 3.38-.52 4.31C3.55 5.67 1.98 6.45.9 7.98c-1.45 2.05-1.7 6.53 3.53 7.7-2.2-1.16-2.67-4.52-.3-6.61-.61 2.03.53 3.33 1.94 2.86 1.39-.47 2.3.53 2.27 1.67-.02.78-.31 1.44-1.13 1.81 3.42-.59 4.78-3.42 4.78-5.56 0-2.84-2.53-3.22-1.25-5.61-1.52.13-2.03 1.13-1.89 2.75.09 1.08-1.02 1.8-1.86 1.33-.67-.41-.66-1.19-.06-1.78C8.18 5.31 8.68 2.45 5.05.32L5.03.3l.02.01z"></path></svg></span>This attention blink can be scientifically regulated by:</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><ol>
<li>Changing the focus of pupil in the eyes.</li>
<li>Closing the eyes and listening to your body, touch and breathing.</li>
<li>Blink your eyes less.</li>
</ol></div></div>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Harikrishnan</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/hkvongit</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="ADHD" term="ADHD"/>
    </entry>
</feed>